<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Applications | NTU Graph Deep Learning Lab</title>
    <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/categories/applications/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/categories/applications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Applications</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Xavier Bresson © 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 16:19:27 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Applications</title>
      <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/categories/applications/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free-hand Sketches</title>
      <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/project/sketches/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 16:19:27 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/project/sketches/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;representation-learning-for-sketches&#34;&gt;Representation Learning for Sketches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human beings have been creating free-hand sketches, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, drawings without precise instruments, since &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cave_painting&#34;&gt;time immemorial&lt;/a&gt;.
Due to the popularity of touchscreen interfaces, machine learning using sketches has emerged as an interesting problem with a myriad of applications:
If we consider sketches as 2D images, We can throw them into off-the-shelf &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.07873&#34;&gt;Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs)&lt;/a&gt;.
While CNNs are designed for &lt;em&gt;static&lt;/em&gt; collections of pixels with &lt;em&gt;dense&lt;/em&gt; colors and textures,
sketches are usually an extremely &lt;em&gt;sparse&lt;/em&gt; sequences of strokes which capture high-level abstractions and ideas. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.googleblog.com/2017/04/teaching-machines-to-draw.html&#34;&gt;Recurrent Neural Networks (RNNs)&lt;/a&gt; stick out as a natural architecture for capturing this temporal nature of sketches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Structure vs. temporal order: can we have the best of both worlds?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sketches-as-graphs&#34;&gt;Sketches as Graphs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are working on a novel representation of free-hand sketches as &lt;strong&gt;sparsely-connected graphs&lt;/strong&gt;. 
We assume that sketches are sets of curves and strokes, which are discretized by a set of points representing the graph nodes.
Each node encodes spatial, temporal and semantic information.
Thus, representing sketches with graphs offers a universal representation that can make use of both the sketch structure (like images) as well as temporal information (like stroke sequences).
To exploit these graph structures, we are developing &lt;strong&gt;Graph Neural Networks (GNNs)&lt;/strong&gt; based on the Transformer model &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03762&#34;&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Vaswani et al.&lt;/em&gt;, 2017]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial Optimization</title>
      <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/project/combinatorial-optimization/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 22:20:35 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/project/combinatorial-optimization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;operations-research-and-combinatorial-problems&#34;&gt;Operations Research and Combinatorial Problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operations_research&#34;&gt;Operations Research (OR)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; started in the first world war as an initiative to use mathematics and computer science to assist military planners in their decisions. Nowadays it is widely used in the industry, including but not limited to transportation, supply chain, energy, finance, and scheduling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OR Problems are formulated as integer constrained optimization, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, with integral or binary variables (called decision variables).
While not all such problems are hard to solve (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, finding the shortest path between two locations), we concentrate on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combinatorial_optimization&#34;&gt;Combinatorial (NP-Hard) problems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. 
NP-Hard problems are &lt;em&gt;impossible&lt;/em&gt; to solve optimally at large scales as exhaustively searching for their solutions is beyond the limits of modern computers.
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelling_salesman_problem&#34;&gt;Travelling Salesman Problem (TSP)&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_spanning_tree&#34;&gt;Minimum Spanning Tree Problem (MST)&lt;/a&gt; are two of the most popular examples for such problems defined using graphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;tsp-gif.gif&#34; alt=&#34;TSP GIF&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;TSP asks the following question: Given a list of cities and the distances between each pair of cities, what is the shortest possible route that visits each city and returns to the origin city? Formally, given a graph, one needs to search the space of permutations to find an optimal sequence of nodes, called a tour, with minimal total edge weights (tour length).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;neural-combinatorial-optimization&#34;&gt;Neural Combinatorial Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although handcrafted heuristic algorithms are able to solve problems such as TSP with up to a million variables,
designing good heuristics often requires significant specialized knowledge and years of trial-and-error.
The state-of-the-art TSP solver, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.uwaterloo.ca/tsp/concorde.html&#34;&gt;Concorde&lt;/a&gt;, leverages &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q8nQTNvCrjE&#34;&gt;over 50 years of research&lt;/a&gt; on linear programming, cutting plane algorithms and branch-and-bound.
At our lab, we&#39;re working on &lt;strong&gt;automating&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;augmenting&lt;/strong&gt; such expert intuition through Machine Learning [&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.06128&#34;&gt;Bengio &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, 2018&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since most problems are highly structured, heuristics take the form of rules or policies to make sequential decisions, &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, determine the TSP tour one city at a time. 
Our research uses deep neural networks to parameterize these policies and train them directly from problem instances.
In particular, &lt;strong&gt;Graph Neural Networks&lt;/strong&gt; are the perfect fit for the task because they naturally operate on the graph structure of these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;pipeline.png&#34; alt=&#34;End-to-end pipeline&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Chemistry</title>
      <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/project/chemistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 22:20:35 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/project/chemistry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
