<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Transformer | NTU Graph Deep Learning Lab</title>
    <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/tags/transformer/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/tags/transformer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Transformer</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Xavier Bresson © 2020 · Made with &amp;hearts; by [Chaitanya Joshi](https://chaitjo.github.io/)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 16:08:39 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/images/icon_hu027d87ac1e37f4f802995042c9999554_21044_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Transformer</title>
      <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/tags/transformer/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transformers are Graph Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/post/transformers-are-gnns/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 16:08:39 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/post/transformers-are-gnns/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Engineer friends often ask me: Graph Deep Learning sounds great, but are there any big commercial success stories? Is it being deployed in practical applications?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the obvious ones&amp;ndash;recommendation systems at &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/pinterest-engineering/pinsage-a-new-graph-convolutional-neural-network-for-web-scale-recommender-systems-88795a107f48&#34;&gt;Pinterest&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.08730&#34;&gt;Alibaba&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.twitter.com/en_us/topics/company/2019/Twitter-acquires-Fabula-AI.html&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ndash;a slightly nuanced success story is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03762&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transformer architecture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which has &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/blog/better-language-models/&#34;&gt;taken&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.blog.google/products/search/search-language-understanding-bert/&#34;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/project/large-scale-pretraining-for-response-generation/&#34;&gt;NLP&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.facebook.com/blog/roberta-an-optimized-method-for-pretraining-self-supervised-nlp-systems/&#34;&gt;industry&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.einstein.ai/introducing-a-conditional-transformer-language-model-for-controllable-generation/&#34;&gt;by&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://nv-adlr.github.io/MegatronLM&#34;&gt;storm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this post, I want to establish links between &lt;a href=&#34;https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/project/spatial-convnets/&#34;&gt;Graph Neural Networks (GNNs)&lt;/a&gt; and Transformers.
I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about the intuitions behind model architectures in the NLP and GNN communities, make connections using equations and figures, and discuss how we could work together to drive progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start by talking about the purpose of model architectures&amp;ndash;&lt;em&gt;representation learning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;representation-learning-for-nlp&#34;&gt;Representation Learning for NLP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a high level, all neural network architectures build &lt;em&gt;representations&lt;/em&gt; of input data as vectors/embeddings, which encode useful statistical and semantic information about the data.
These &lt;em&gt;latent&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;hidden&lt;/em&gt; representations can then be used for performing something useful, such as classifying an image or translating a sentence.
The neural network &lt;em&gt;learns&lt;/em&gt; to build better-and-better representations by receiving feedback, usually via error/loss functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Natural Language Processing (NLP), conventionally, &lt;strong&gt;Recurrent Neural Networks&lt;/strong&gt; (RNNs) build representations of each word in a sentence in a sequential manner, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;one word at a time&lt;/strong&gt;.
Intuitively, we can imagine an RNN layer as a conveyor belt, with the words being processed on it &lt;em&gt;autoregressively&lt;/em&gt; from left to right.
At the end, we get a hidden feature for each word in the sentence, which we pass to the next RNN layer or use for our NLP tasks of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend Chris Olah&amp;rsquo;s legendary blog for recaps on &lt;a href=&#34;http://colah.github.io/posts/2015-08-Understanding-LSTMs/&#34;&gt;RNNs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://colah.github.io/posts/2014-07-NLP-RNNs-Representations/&#34;&gt;representation learning&lt;/a&gt; for NLP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;rnn-transf-nlp.jpg&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;rnn-transf-nlp.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially introduced for machine translation, &lt;strong&gt;Transformers&lt;/strong&gt; have gradually replaced RNNs in mainstream NLP.
The architecture takes a fresh approach to representation learning: Doing away with recurrence entirely, Transformers build features of each word using an &lt;a href=&#34;https://distill.pub/2016/augmented-rnns/&#34;&gt;attention&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://lilianweng.github.io/lil-log/2018/06/24/attention-attention.html&#34;&gt;mechanism&lt;/a&gt; to figure out how important &lt;strong&gt;all the other words&lt;/strong&gt; in the sentence are w.r.t. to the aforementioned word.
Knowing this, the word&amp;rsquo;s updated features are simply the sum of linear transformations of the features of all the words, weighted by their importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2017, this idea sounded very radical, because the NLP community was so used to the sequential&amp;ndash;one-word-at-a-time&amp;ndash;style of processing text with RNNs. The title of the paper probably added fuel to the fire!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a recap, Yannic Kilcher made an excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iDulhoQ2pro&#34;&gt;video overview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;breaking-down-the-transformer&#34;&gt;Breaking down the Transformer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s develop intuitions about the architecture by translating the previous paragraph into the language of mathematical symbols and vectors.
We update the hidden feature $h$ of the $i$&#39;th word in a sentence $\mathcal{S}$ from layer $\ell$ to layer $\ell+1$ as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
h_{i}^{\ell+1} = \text{Attention} \left( Q^{\ell} h_{i}^{\ell} \ , K^{\ell} h_{j}^{\ell} \ , V^{\ell} h_{j}^{\ell} \right),
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
i.e.,\ h_{i}^{\ell+1} = \sum_{j \in \mathcal{S}} w_{ij} \left( V^{\ell} h_{j}^{\ell} \right),
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\text{where} \ w_{ij} = \text{softmax}_j \left( Q^{\ell} h_{i}^{\ell} \cdot  K^{\ell} h_{j}^{\ell} \right),
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $j \in \mathcal{S}$ denotes the set of words in the sentence and $Q^{\ell}, K^{\ell}, V^{\ell}$ are learnable linear weights (denoting the &lt;strong&gt;Q&lt;/strong&gt;uery, &lt;strong&gt;K&lt;/strong&gt;ey and &lt;strong&gt;V&lt;/strong&gt;alue for the attention computation, respectively).
The attention mechanism is performed parallelly for each word in the sentence to obtain their updated features in &lt;em&gt;one shot&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;another plus point for Transformers over RNNs, which update features word-by-word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can understand the attention mechanism better through the following pipeline:&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;attention-block.jpg&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;attention-block.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking in the features of the word $h_{i}^{\ell}$ and the set of other words in the sentence ${ h_{j}^{\ell} ;\ \forall j \in \mathcal{S} }$, we compute the attention weights $w_{ij}$ for each pair $(i,j)$ through the dot-product, followed by a softmax across all $j$&#39;s. Finally, we produce the updated word feature $h_{i}^{\ell+1}$ for word $i$ by summing over all ${ h_{j}^{\ell} }$&#39;s weighted by their corresponding $w_{ij}$. Each word in the sentence parallelly undergoes the same pipeline to update its features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;multi-head-attention-mechanism&#34;&gt;Multi-head Attention mechanism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting this dot-product attention mechanism to work proves to be tricky&amp;ndash;bad random initializations can de-stabilize the learning process.
We can overcome this by parallelly performing multiple &amp;lsquo;heads&amp;rsquo; of attention and concatenating the result (with each head now having separate learnable  weights):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
h_{i}^{\ell+1} = \text{Concat} \left( \text{head}_1, \ldots, \text{head}_K \right) O^{\ell},
$$
$$
\text{head}_k = \text{Attention} \left(  Q^{k,\ell} h_{i}^{\ell} \ , K^{k, \ell} h_{j}^{\ell} \ , V^{k, \ell} h_{j}^{\ell} \right),
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $Q^{k,\ell}, K^{k,\ell}, V^{k,\ell}$ are the learnable weights of the $k$&#39;th attention head and $O^{\ell}$ is a down-projection to match the dimensions of $h_i^{\ell+1}$ and $h_i^{\ell}$ across layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple heads allow the attention mechanism to essentially &amp;lsquo;hedge its bets&amp;rsquo;, looking at different transformations or aspects of the hidden features from the previous layer.
We&amp;rsquo;ll talk more about this later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;scale-issues-and-the-feed-forward-sub-layer&#34;&gt;Scale issues and the Feed-forward sub-layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key issue motivating the final Transformer architecture is that the features for words &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the attention mechanism might be at &lt;strong&gt;different scales&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;magnitudes&lt;/strong&gt;:
(1) This can be due to some words having very sharp or very distributed attention weights $w_{ij}$ when summing over the features of the other words.
(2) At the individual feature/vector entries level, concatenating across multiple attention heads&amp;ndash;each of which might output values at different scales&amp;ndash;can lead to the entries of the final vector $h_{i}^{\ell+1}$ having a wide range of values.
Following conventional ML wisdom, it seems reasonable to add a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nealjean.com/ml/neural-network-normalization/&#34;&gt;normalization layer&lt;/a&gt; into the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transformers overcome issue (2) with &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1607.06450&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LayerNorm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which normalizes and learns an affine transformation at the feature level.
Additionally, &lt;strong&gt;scaling the dot-product&lt;/strong&gt; attention by the square-root of the feature dimension helps counteract issue (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the authors propose another &amp;lsquo;trick&amp;rsquo; to control the scale issue: &lt;strong&gt;a position-wise 2-layer MLP&lt;/strong&gt; with a special structure.
After the multi-head attention, they project $h_i^{\ell+1}$ to a (absurdly) higher dimension by a learnable weight, where it undergoes the ReLU non-linearity, and is then projected back to its original dimension followed by another normalization:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
h_i^{\ell+1} = \text{LN} \left( \text{MLP} \left( \text{LN} \left( h_i^{\ell+1} \right) \right) \right)
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what the exact intuition behind the over-parameterized feed-forward sub-layer was and nobody seems to be asking questions about it, too! I suppose LayerNorm and scaled dot-products didn&amp;rsquo;t completely solve the issues highlighted, so the big MLP is a sort of hack to re-scale the feature vectors independently of each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:chaitanya.joshi@ntu.edu.sg&#34;&gt;Email me&lt;/a&gt; if you know more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final picture of a Transformer layer looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;transformer-block.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;transformer-block.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transformer architecture is also extremely amenable to very deep networks, enabling the NLP community to &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.10683&#34;&gt;scale&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.08361&#34;&gt;up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in terms of both model parameters and, by extension, data.
&lt;strong&gt;Residual connections&lt;/strong&gt; between the inputs and outputs of each multi-head attention sub-layer and the feed-forward sub-layer are key for stacking Transformer layers (but omitted from the diagram for clarity).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gnns-build-representations-of-graphs&#34;&gt;GNNs build representations of graphs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a step away from NLP for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) or Graph Convolutional Networks (GCNs) build representations of nodes and edges in graph data.
They do so through &lt;strong&gt;neighbourhood aggregation&lt;/strong&gt; (or message passing), where each node gathers features from its neighbours to update its representation of the &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; graph structure around it.
Stacking several GNN layers enables the model to propagate each node&amp;rsquo;s features over the entire graph&amp;ndash;from its neighbours to the neighbours&amp;rsquo; neighbours, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;gnn-social-network.jpg&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;gnn-social-network.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the example of this emoji social network: The node features produced by the GNN can be used for predictive tasks such as identifying the most influential members or proposing potential connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their most basic form, GNNs update the hidden features $h$ of node $i$ (for example, 😆) at layer $\ell$ via a non-linear transformation of the node&amp;rsquo;s own features $h_i^{\ell}$ added to the aggregation of features $h_j^{\ell}$ from each neighbouring node $j \in \mathcal{N}(i)$:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
h_{i}^{\ell+1} =  \sigma \Big( U^{\ell} h_{i}^{\ell} + \sum_{j \in \mathcal{N}(i)} \left( V^{\ell} h_{j}^{\ell} \right)  \Big),
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $U^{\ell}, V^{\ell}$ are learnable weight matrices of the GNN layer and $\sigma$ is a non-linearity such as ReLU.
In the example, $\mathcal{N}$(😆) $=$ { 😘, 😎, 😜, 🤩 }.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The summation over the neighbourhood nodes $j \in \mathcal{N}(i)$ can be replaced by other input size-invariant &lt;strong&gt;aggregation functions&lt;/strong&gt; such as simple mean/max or something more powerful, such as a weighted sum via an &lt;a href=&#34;https://petar-v.com/GAT/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;attention mechanism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does that sound familiar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe a pipeline will help make the connection:&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;gnn-block.jpg&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;gnn-block.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    If we were to do multiple parallel heads of neighbourhood aggregation and replace summation over the neighbours $j$ with the attention mechanism, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, a weighted sum, we&amp;rsquo;d get the &lt;b&gt;Graph Attention Network&lt;/b&gt; (GAT). Add normalization and the feed-forward MLP, and voila, we have a &lt;b&gt;Graph Transformer&lt;/b&gt;!
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sentences-are-fully-connected-word-graphs&#34;&gt;Sentences are fully-connected word graphs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the connection more explicit, consider a sentence as a fully-connected graph, where each word is connected to every other word.
Now, we can use a GNN to build features for each node (word) in the graph (sentence), which we can then perform NLP tasks with.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;gnn-nlp.jpg&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;gnn-nlp.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly, this is what Transformers are doing: they are &lt;strong&gt;GNNs with multi-head attention&lt;/strong&gt; as the neighbourhood aggregation function.
Whereas standard GNNs aggregate features from their local neighbourhood nodes $j \in \mathcal{N}(i)$,
Transformers for NLP treat the entire sentence $\mathcal{S}$ as the local neighbourhood, aggregating features from each word $j \in \mathcal{S}$ at each layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, various problem-specific tricks&amp;ndash;such as position encodings, causal/masked aggregation, learning rate schedules and extensive pre-training&amp;ndash;are essential for the success of Transformers but seldom seem in the GNN community.
At the same time, looking at Transformers from a GNN perspective could inspire us to get rid of a lot of the &lt;em&gt;bells and whistles&lt;/em&gt; in the architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-can-we-learn-from-each-other&#34;&gt;What can we learn from each other?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we&amp;rsquo;ve established a connection between Transformers and GNNs, let me throw some ideas around&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;are-fully-connected-graphs-the-best-input-format-for-nlp&#34;&gt;Are fully-connected graphs the best input format for NLP?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before statistical NLP and ML, linguists like Noam Chomsky focused on developing fomal theories of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syntactic_Structures&#34;&gt;linguistic structure&lt;/a&gt;, such as &lt;strong&gt;syntax trees/graphs&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1503.00075&#34;&gt;Tree LSTMs&lt;/a&gt; already tried this, but maybe Transformers/GNNs are better architectures for bringing the world of linguistic theory and statistical NLP closer?&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;syntax-tree.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;syntax-tree.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-to-learn-long-term-dependencies&#34;&gt;How to learn long-term dependencies?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue with fully-connected graphs is that they make learning very long-term dependencies between words difficult.
This is simply due to how the number of edges in the graph &lt;strong&gt;scales quadratically&lt;/strong&gt; with the number of nodes, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, in an $n$ word sentence, a Transformer/GNN would be doing computations over $n^2$ pairs of words. Things get out of hand for very large $n$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NLP community&amp;rsquo;s perspective on the long sequences and dependencies problem is interesting:
Making the attention mechanism &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/blog/sparse-transformer/&#34;&gt;sparse&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.facebook.com/blog/making-transformer-networks-simpler-and-more-efficient/&#34;&gt;adaptive&lt;/a&gt; in terms of input size, adding &lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.googleblog.com/2019/01/transformer-xl-unleashing-potential-of.html&#34;&gt;recurrence&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://deepmind.com/blog/article/A_new_model_and_dataset_for_long-range_memory&#34;&gt;compression&lt;/a&gt; into each layer,
and using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pragmatic.ml/reformer-deep-dive/&#34;&gt;Locality Sensitive Hashing&lt;/a&gt; for efficient attention
are all promising new ideas for better Transformers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to see ideas from the GNN community thrown into the mix, &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.04070&#34;&gt;Binary Partitioning&lt;/a&gt; for sentence &lt;strong&gt;graph sparsification&lt;/strong&gt; seems like another exciting approach.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;long-term-depend.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;long-term-depend.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;are-transformers-learning-neural-syntax&#34;&gt;Are Transformers learning &amp;lsquo;neural syntax&amp;rsquo;?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been &lt;a href=&#34;https://pair-code.github.io/interpretability/bert-tree/&#34;&gt;several&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.05950&#34;&gt;interesting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.04341&#34;&gt;papers&lt;/a&gt; from the NLP community on what Transformers might be learning.
The basic premise is that performing attention on all word pairs in a sentence&amp;ndash;with the purpose of identifying which pairs are the most interesting&amp;ndash;enables Transformers to learn something like a &lt;strong&gt;task-specific syntax&lt;/strong&gt;.
Different heads in the multi-head attention might also be &amp;lsquo;looking&amp;rsquo; at different syntactic properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In graph terms, by using GNNs on full graphs, can we recover the most important edges&amp;ndash;and what they might entail&amp;ndash;from how the GNN performs neighbourhood aggregation at each layer?
I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.07913&#34;&gt;not so convinced&lt;/a&gt; by this view yet.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;attention-heads.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;attention-heads.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-multiple-heads-of-attention-why-attention&#34;&gt;Why multiple heads of attention? Why attention?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m more sympathetic to the optimization view of the multi-head mechanism&amp;ndash;having multiple attention heads &lt;strong&gt;improves learning&lt;/strong&gt; and overcomes &lt;strong&gt;bad random initializations&lt;/strong&gt;.
For instance, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lena-voita.github.io/posts/acl19_heads.html&#34;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.10650&#34;&gt;papers&lt;/a&gt; showed that Transformer heads can be &amp;lsquo;pruned&amp;rsquo; or removed &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; training without significant performance impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multi-head neighbourhood aggregation mechanisms have also proven effective in GNNs, &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt;, GAT uses the same multi-head attention and &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1611.08402&#34;&gt;MoNet&lt;/a&gt; uses multiple &lt;em&gt;Gaussian kernels&lt;/em&gt; for aggregating features.
Although invented to stabilize attention mechanisms, could the multi-head trick become standard for squeezing out extra model performance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, GNNs with simpler aggregation functions such as sum or max do not require multiple aggregation heads for stable training.
Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be nice for Transformers if we didn&amp;rsquo;t have to compute pair-wise compatibilities between each word pair in the sentence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could Transformers benefit from ditching attention, altogether? Yann Dauphin and collaborators&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03122&#34;&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.10430&#34;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt; suggests an alternative &lt;strong&gt;ConvNet architecture&lt;/strong&gt;.
Transformers, too, might ultimately be doing &lt;a href=&#34;http://jbcordonnier.com/posts/attention-cnn/&#34;&gt;something&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ChrSzegedy/status/1232148457810538496&#34;&gt;similar&lt;/a&gt; to ConvNets!&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;attention-conv.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img data-src=&#34;attention-conv.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-is-training-transformers-so-hard&#34;&gt;Why is training Transformers so hard?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading new Transformer papers makes me feel that training these models requires something akin to &lt;em&gt;black magic&lt;/em&gt; when determining the best &lt;strong&gt;learning rate schedule, warmup strategy&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;decay settings&lt;/strong&gt;.
This could simply be because the models are so huge and the NLP tasks studied are so challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.01787&#34;&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.06764&#34;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.04745&#34;&gt;suggest&lt;/a&gt; that it could also be due to the specific permutation of normalization and residual connections within the architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I enjoyed reading the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DeepMind?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@DeepMind&lt;/a&gt; Transformer paper, but why is training these models such dark magic? &amp;quot;For word-based LM we used 16, 000 warmup steps with 500, 000 decay steps and sacrifice 9,000 goats.&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/dP49GTa4ze&#34;&gt;https://t.co/dP49GTa4ze&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/1K3Fx4s3M8&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/1K3Fx4s3M8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Chaitanya Joshi (@chaitjo) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/chaitjo/status/1229335421806501888?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 17, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;	
&lt;p&gt;At this point I&amp;rsquo;m ranting, but this makes me sceptical: Do we really need multiple heads of expensive pair-wise attention, overparameterized MLP sub-layers, and complicated learning schedules?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we really need massive models with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.technologyreview.com/s/613630/training-a-single-ai-model-can-emit-as-much-carbon-as-five-cars-in-their-lifetimes/&#34;&gt;massive carbon footprints&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shouldn&amp;rsquo;t architectures with good &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1806.01261&#34;&gt;inductive biases&lt;/a&gt; for the task at hand be easier to train?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;further-reading&#34;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To dive deep into the Transformer architecture from an NLP perspective, check out these amazing blog posts: &lt;a href=&#34;http://jalammar.github.io/illustrated-transformer/&#34;&gt;The Illustrated Transformer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://nlp.seas.harvard.edu/2018/04/03/attention.html&#34;&gt;The Annotated Transformer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, this blog isn&amp;rsquo;t the first to link GNNs and Transformers:
Here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipam.wistia.com/medias/1zgl4lq6nh&#34;&gt;an excellent talk&lt;/a&gt; by Arthur Szlam on the history and connection between Attention/Memory Networks, GNNs and Transformers.
Similarly, DeepMind&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1806.01261&#34;&gt;star-studded position paper&lt;/a&gt; introduces the &lt;em&gt;Graph Networks&lt;/em&gt; framework, unifying all these ideas.
For a code walkthrough, the DGL team has &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.dgl.ai/en/latest/tutorials/models/4_old_wines/7_transformer.html&#34;&gt;a nice tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on seq2seq as a graph problem and building Transformers as GNNs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In our next post, we&amp;rsquo;ll be doing the reverse: using GNN architectures as Transformers for NLP (based on the Transformers library by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/huggingface/transformers&#34;&gt;🤗 HuggingFace&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/publication/xu-2019-multi/&#34;&gt;a recent paper&lt;/a&gt; applying Transformers to sketch graphs. Do check it out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;updates&#34;&gt;Updates&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post is also available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@chaitjo/transformers-are-graph-neural-networks-bca9f75412aa?source=friends_link&amp;amp;sk=c54de873b2cec3db70166a6cf0b41d3e&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;, and has been translated to &lt;a href=&#34;https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/DABEcNf1hHahlZFMttiT2g&#34;&gt;Chinese&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://habr.com/ru/post/491576/&#34;&gt;Russian&lt;/a&gt;.
Do join the discussion on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/chaitjo/status/1233220586358181888?s=20&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/MachineLearning/comments/fb86mo/d_transformers_are_graph_neural_networks_blog/&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=22518263&#34;&gt;HackerNews&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Transformers are a special case of Graph Neural Networks. This may be obvious to some, but the following blog post does a good job at explaining these important concepts. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/H8LT2F7LqC&#34;&gt;https://t.co/H8LT2F7LqC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Oriol Vinyals (@OriolVinyalsML) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/OriolVinyalsML/status/1233783593626951681?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 29, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Graph Transformer for Free-Hand Sketch Recognition</title>
      <link>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/publication/xu-2019-multi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://graphdeeplearning.github.io/publication/xu-2019-multi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
